He is the master terrorist [music]
behind dozens of murderous attacks on
innocent civilians. [music]
>> His hands are covered with Jewish blood.
>> As far as Israel's [music] concerned, he
was an arch-terrorist.
>> There is no choice but to take [music]
him out.
Tasked with the operation is Israel's
elite special forces unit.
>> SAYERET MATKAL IS NOTHING SHORT OF
legendary or mythical. [music]
>> But with that target hiding in an enemy
nation 1,500 miles from Israel, this
will be one of the most ambitious
operations ever mounted.
>> You go in,
you kill him, you go out.
Perfect assassination. [music]
>> This is the true story of the Sayeret
Matkal mission to kill [music]
Abu Jihad.
>> [music]
>> In the dead of night, three terrorists
infiltrate the Israeli border.
>> This was a raid by
Palestinians.
>> They armed themselves from a secret
weapons cache that the PLO had in Egypt.
>> Carrying AK-47s, they evade the Israeli
border patrols.
>> They crossed Israel's southern Negev
desert.
>> Their presence remains a secret until
when they reach a remote desert road.
They hijack A PASSING CAR.
>> [music]
>> ISRAELI INTELLIGENCE RECEIVE reports
about the car hijacking.
They now know [music] armed gunmen are
on the loose inside Israel.
But they have no [music] idea what their
target is.
>> This uh triggered a an enormous security
alert in southern Israel. Roadblocks
were put up.
>> [music]
>> An hour later, the gunmen's car is
sighted approaching a high security
area.
>> It was
>> [music]
>> not far from Dimona,
which is the site of Israel's nuclear
reactor.
>> It becomes clear that the terrorists are
planning to attack the Dimona reactor,
Israel's most important military
facility.
>> Yes, the one where Israel has nuclear
weapons but has never admitted that they
have nuclear weapons.
>> With the top-secret facility at risk,
army units race to intercept the
terrorists before they can reach their
target.
Realizing that Israeli forces are
closing down on them, the Palestinians
suddenly change their plans.
>> The group kidnapped a bus that was
bringing workers from the Dimona nuclear
reactor back home.
>> [music]
>> Some of the passengers managed to
escape.
But 11 are trapped.
>> [music]
>> 10 are women.
Israeli security forces surround the bus
and try to negotiate with the
terrorists.
But the gunmen are not interested in
negotiating.
Then they turn their weapons on the
hostages.
Now the security forces have to go in.
>> You know, from here
if you're not going to respond, more
people going to die.
>> First they get into position.
Then they strike.
In a matter [music] of seconds, Israeli
soldiers take over the bus, killing all
three of the terrorists.
But quick as they are,
they are not fast enough.
>> Three of the workers at the Dimona plant
were killed.
>> Two of the victims are young mothers.
It becomes known as the mothers bus
attack.
>> [music]
>> Even in a nation used to terrorism,
this is still a shocking act.
>> The Dimona bus attack was different from
what was going on.
>> This one was such a horrific attack that
targeted not only innocent people, but
mothers and women. That's really the
most raw nerve in Israel.
>> But even as the mourners gather, Israeli
intelligence agencies have already
identified the man behind the attack.
>> [music]
>> The man they are after
is Abu Jihad.
In Arabic, Abu Jihad means father of the
struggle. The Israelis know that this is
a title used by a leading Palestinian
commander.
>> Abu Jihad is a nom de guerre like a lot
of Palestinian names. His real name is
Khalil Wazir.
>> Abu Jihad is the legendary militant
commander of the the PLO.
>> In the Palestinian organization, of
course, he was admired as one [music] of
their top leaders.
>> He is the number two man in the
Palestinian Liberation Organization
>> [music]
>> and heads its military wing.
>> Abu Jihad was in charge of operations of
El Fatah.
>> Under Abu Jihad's command, El Fatah have
undertaken dozens of attacks on Israel.
>> He had organized and planned some quite
significant Palestinian actions.
Innocent people have been killed often
in brutal circumstances.
>> As far as Israel's concerned, he was an
arch terrorist.
>> Abu Jihad was a very dangerous man.
>> Abu Jihad is such a threat to Israel
that for 20 years they have been trying
to take him out.
>> The hunt for Abu Jihad was uh conducted
throughout the years.
There were numerous attempts on his
life.
All of them failed.
>> [music]
>> Israeli military intelligence first
tried to kill Abu Jihad in Damascus with
a car bomb.
>> [music]
>> They missed.
A decade later, the Israeli Air Force
tried to kill him in an air strike on
Beirut.
But again,
he walked away.
The Mother's Bus attack is proof that
the master terrorist has reared his head
once more.
But the threat he poses may be worse
than just terrorism.
The Israelis believe that Abu Jihad is
also behind the biggest challenge to
their authority
that they have ever faced.
For 3 months, the Palestinian population
of Israel
has been in revolt.
>> There was this uprising against their
rule.
There were large crowds of people, often
young people, throwing stones at Israeli
forces. It had elements of an armed
uprising.
>> Its military was in the West Bank
dealing with a wide array of uh of
protest.
>> It has become known as the Intifada,
the uprising.
And Israel believes that the hand that
controls it is Abu Jihad's.
>> He claimed responsibility for the
outbreak of the Palestinian Intifada.
He said, "I was the one ordering the
troops, ordering the demonstrators to go
to the street."
>> Israel cannot allow the insurrection to
continue.
>> The Intifada caused an enormous [music]
international damage to Israeli prestige
worldwide.
They felt they have to get back at Abu
Jihad. They felt that he couldn't be
allowed to get away with that.
>> And the man who decides to deal with Abu
Jihad
is Yitzhak Rabin, Israel's Minister of
Defense.
>> Yitzhak Rabin who was basically leading
the Israeli intelligence and security
forces.
>> Rabin was quite a hardliner. [music] He
was a military man through and through.
>> His whole concept of peace was based on
the fact that Israel had to be strong
and it had to defend itself.
He was simply very strongly in targeting
those terrorists that were attacking
[music] Israelis.
>> Rabin decides that Israel must kill Abu
Jihad.
>> [music]
>> But immediately Rabin faces a problem.
Abu Jihad is a long way from Israeli
shores.
Israeli intelligence have traced Abu
Jihad to Tunis, North Africa.
1,500 miles from Israel.
The city has become the new headquarters
for the Palestinian Liberation
Organization.
>> That was the the place where the the PLO
or headquarters was, far away from
Israel on the coast of Africa.
>> Abu Jihad and other key Palestinian
leaders have homes in a quiet suburb of
the Tunisian capital.
>> He lived with his family in a villa in a
beach side neighborhood of Tunis.
>> Being so far away from Israel, Abu Jihad
felt quite confident and safe.
He didn't think that Israeli
intelligence would be able to get so
far, so remotely from Israel.
>> But he is wrong.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Abu Jihad is already under the watchful
eye of Israel's intelligence service,
Mossad.
>> [music]
>> These people are followed, these people
are tracked.
>> They knew where he was.
>> [music]
>> Israel's intelligence agency carried out
surveillance of the area of
Tunis [music] where Abu Jihad was living
along with other PLO leaders.
>> 4 days after the Mothers Bus attack,
Rabin orders Mossad to come up with a
way to kill Abu Jihad.
Initially, the agency is confident that
they can do it themselves. [music]
>> They told Defense Minister Rabin that
they could come up with an operational
plan to assassinate Abu Jihad in Tunisia
within 30 days.
>> Mossad come up with various alternatives
for killing Abu Jihad.
>> By a sniper.
By exploding his car.
By planting a booby trap, explosive
where he was driving from his house to
his office.
By poisoning him.
By uh firing rockets on his house.
All sorts of possible operations.
>> But Rabin rejects them all.
None of these options guarantee that Abu
Jihad will be killed.
With the Intifada raging, they simply
cannot afford to miss.
As far as Rabin is concerned,
there is only one way to ensure success.
To kill him
at point-blank range.
>> It was decided that Abu Jihad is going
to be killed in his house.
>> But killing the PLO's military commander
in his home, 1,500 miles from Israel,
will be no easy task.
>> Far harder to target somebody in Tunis
than in somewhere that is, you know,
20 minutes flying time or just across
one of Israel's borders.
>> And so, at the end of the day, Mossad
came to Yitzhak Rabin
and said, "We are not able to
>> [music]
>> do this alone."
>> Skilled assassins as they are,
getting a hit team inside Abu Jihad's
house without being discovered
is beyond even the Mossad.
So, Rabin now calls upon a highly
secretive special operations brigade,
famed for their ability to strike at
Israel's enemies wherever they may try
to hide.
>> When Israel wants to strike, Israeli
leaders turn [music] to a special unit
of the Israeli military.
>> The immediate candidate to perform the
assassination is the General Staff
Reconnaissance Unit.
>> But in Israel,
they are known by another name.
>> [music]
>> In English, they are known as the unit.
But in Hebrew, they call them Sayeret
Matkal.
>> Sayeret Matkal in Israel is nothing
short of legendary or mythical.
>> [music]
>> It's essentially the top unit in the
army.
>> It's sort of a byword for an elite unit.
[music] There are others, but that's the
sort of creme de la creme.
>> It's a unit modeled after the British
SAS.
SEAL teams are similar to it. Delta
Force is similar to it.
>> Like these other special forces units,
the Sayeret [music] Matkal are experts
at killing people.
>> They're thought of as assassination
specialists.
>> They're willing [music] to sacrifice
everything for their country.
>> Commandos [music] train intensively in
survival skills,
marksmanship,
and hand-to-hand combat.
>> Their job is to go on special operations
that are considered beyond the scope of
your regular troops.
>> Only the very best of the Israeli
military are recruited into the Sayeret
Matkal.
>> [music]
>> You're looking in an elite unit for a
person that in no time can [music]
concentrate and do the things fast.
You're looking for [music] a person that
will never give up on himself.
>> These men have the reputation [music]
for accomplishing things, getting things
done.
>> [music]
>> That reputation was cemented by a
legendary operation that took place
[music] in 1976.
Terrorists hijack an Air France plane
with more than 100 Israeli Jewish
civilians on board.
The plane is diverted to [music] the
Ugandan capital, Entebbe.
When Uganda's dictator Idi Amin [music]
decides to cooperate with the
terrorists, Israel calls on the Sayeret
Matkal.
>> The unit Sayeret Matkal took [music]
something like a few weeks to train on
the model of the airplane.
To fly to Entebbe and to give the right
solution for the incident.
>> That solution is for the Sayeret Matkal
commandos to disguise themselves as
members [music] of the Ugandan army.
Once on the ground, [music]
the unit strikes.
>> They went in there, did [music] a
counter-terrorist mission over a
thousand miles from home,
killed the terrorists,
and got out of there alive.
>> 102 hostages were rescued and returned
to Israel with only three civilian
casualties.
>> [music]
>> That lightning raid, of course, became
legendary.
>> And that was the beginning of their
reputation as being a [music] hardcore
unit.
>> Rabin believes there is no other unit
better suited for the task of taking out
Abu Jihad.
So, he puts in a call to a man who had
been one of the architects of the
Entebbe mission. [music]
He is Israel's most decorated soldier
>> [music]
>> and a living legend.
Ehud Barak.
>> [music]
>> Ehud Barak was a head of Sayeret Matkal,
one of the most famous commanders of
Sayeret Matkal.
>> He was in a position then as being a
chief of staff or head of military
intelligence.
>> Very serious guy, very smart guy, very
sharp guy, very decorated [music] guy.
>> Rabin orders Barak
>> [music]
>> to draw up a plan for the Sayeret Matkal
to assassinate Abu Jihad.
It will be known as Operation Show of
Force.
Now Barak demonstrates one of the
hallmarks of the [music] Sayeret Matkal,
meticulous planning.
The key will be finding out as much as
he can about conditions on the ground.
>> They, more than anybody, know the
importance of intelligence and good
intelligence.
>> Despite the distance, if everything was
carefully looked at in advance, there
was a reasonable chance that they could
be able to get away with it.
>> [music]
>> First, Barak has Mossad send more agents
to Tunisia.
>> [music]
>> Previously, Mossad had been simply
keeping tabs on Abu Jihad. [music]
Now they are tasked with gathering
detailed information on his every
movement.
>> The Mossad sent people into Tunisia
posing as either tourists or business
people, very routine again for the
Mossad.
>> [music]
>> They were sent to Tunisia to check all
various questions that came from Sayeret
>> Matkal.
>> Posing as Lebanese Arabs, the new team
liaises with the agents already embedded
in Tunis.
The agents monitor Abu Jihad's journeys
around the city.
>> Israeli intelligence was updated of the
tiniest details of Abu Jihad daily
>> [music]
>> routine and daily daily schedule.
>> The agents listen in on telephone calls
to his home.
>> [music]
>> The Mossad would use electronic means to
intercept communications and listen in.
So, they were confident that they would
know when [music] Abu Jihad is at home.
>> Watching and listening [music] to his
every move, the Mossad team soon learn
the vital information that Barack needs
to [music] launch his operation.
>> Who
is in the house with Abu Jihad? How the
house is built? Who is sleeping in each
room?
How many guards? How far is [music] the
police station?
>> They know the height of the perimeter
walls, the types of windows, doors, and
locks, the distance between the rooms.
They soon know every aspect of the
villa's defenses.
>> They know exactly [music] where he is
and on what floor of the building and
when he goes to sleep and when he comes
and when he goes and where his
bodyguards going to be, etc.
>> Armed with the intelligence from Mossad,
back in Israel,
Barack begins to draw up plans for the
operation.
>> And so, Sayeret Matkal was starting to
plan how to to take out Abu Jihad.
>> The plan Barack [music] develops is to
send in a small team of commandos to
assault the villa under cover of
darkness.
But, it will only work
>> [music]
>> if it is carefully choreographed.
>> The preparation and planning [music] is
the most important thing
in a mission for the special forces
soldier or the special forces [music]
unit.
>> They construct their plan using the
detailed Mossad intelligence.
>> And they built a small model
which is an exact copying of the house.
>> Barak marks out the guard posts and
points of entry.
>> They get all their intelligence together
and then they have to figure out the
best route [music] in to that target.
>> Different strategies for the assault are
debated in order to minimize the risk of
failure.
>> The soldiers are smart and they have a
lot of experience and if they have a
good idea then the idea [music] is taken
and the plan is changed.
>> Once this is agreed,
commandos mark out the exact footprint
of the villa.
>> [music]
>> They practice the assault
again
and again.
>> That was something that Israeli
intelligence and the Sayeret Matkal
commandos frequently did. They never
wanted to leave anything to chance.
>> Like every other secret or special
operation, you should train.
Train for THE EXACT STEPS,
>> [screaming]
>> FOR THE exact performance of yourself
and others and and so on.
But expect the unexpected.
>> The next stage is to practice the
mission in real conditions.
>> Sayeret Matkal asked few people to
donate
a house in Israel not far away from the
beach for rehearsals.
House is quite similar to that of Abu
Jihad.
>> And again and again practice the assault
in Israel before embarking on the
mission.
>> Whilst the commandos are practicing for
the assault on the villa,
Barak turns his attentions to one
outstanding issue.
That means getting the commando unit the
1,500 miles to Tunisia safely and
secretly.
>> All arms of Israeli power would be
involved here. Uh the Mossad, uh the
military intelligence, the navy, the air
force.
>> Barak mobilizes the entire Israeli
military.
>> [music]
>> First, the navy will take the commandos
from Israel to Tunisian waters in
missile boats.
>> It was a huge armada of ships,
airplanes, cargo ships, carrying
helicopters
>> above them. Barak orders the air force
to be ready with an emergency evacuation
[music] plan.
>> Sayeret Matkal is under the coverage of
the air force
in order to be evacuated if something
really bad happens.
>> It is an almost unprecedented mission in
its size and ambition.
>> This was a huge operation. Thousands of
soldiers and intelligence officers
[music]
from the navy, Mossad, military
intelligence.
>> [music]
>> Having arranged how to get the commandos
to [music] Tunisia,
Barak now focuses on a very particular
problem.
The nearest landing beach
is 2 and 1/2 miles from the villa.
This presents him with two problems.
>> The first is how to get Sayid Mattkal to
the house.
And the second was how to get them back
safely and live after the assassination.
>> How can Barak get the team through the
Tunisian streets without them being
detected [music] by either the
Palestinians or the Tunisian police?
>> Bearing in mind Tunisia is a an Arab
country and not a democratic state. It's
a sort of a police state far away from
Israel.
>> They have to get there quickly
without drawing attention.
So they need an insertion plan.
>> So Barak comes up with an ingenious
method to get the commandos to and from
the villa without being detected.
First they will arrange a distraction to
clear the area of police.
>> We expecting local forces [music]
to intervene.
So you give an a notice to the police
[music]
the local police that something happens
far away on the other side of the city.
So everyone is concentrated there. You
have [music] time to to go.
>> Next, [music] the Mossad agents on the
ground will rent cars and drive them to
the beachfront.
There they will collect the commandos
>> [music]
>> and ferry them to a location near to the
villa.
>> Those rented cars were placed on the
beach in Tunis
to make sure that no suspicions would be
aroused.
>> [music]
>> The Mossad agents will park the cars
near Abu Jihad's home.
But the commandos will have to walk the
final few yards to the villa on foot.
>> [music]
>> This is when they will be most exposed.
To get them the last few hundred yards,
Barak turns to his own experiences.
15 years earlier, Barak was involved in
one of the most remarkable missions in
the history of the Sayeret Matkal.
The unit was sent into Beirut,
a heart of enemy territory.
>> [music]
>> They were sent to kill the men behind
the slaughter of 11 Israeli athletes at
the Munich Olympics.
To infiltrate the city undetected,
Barak and the others employed a very
unusual disguise.
>> Some of them are dressed as women in
order to not to distract attention that
just a group of men is walking in the
street.
It's always easier to have men and women
together.
>> [music]
>> Their disguises allowed the unit to
disperse through the city undetected and
launch multiple synchronized attacks.
At the end of that operation, 15 known
terrorists were dead.
Now Barak's team will play the same
trick in Tunisia in order to get to Abu
Jihad's villa undetected.
>> The Israelis felt that they could do
that even in Tunisia, even 1,500 miles
away. So, that playbook was turned to
once again.
>> This leaves Barak with [music] one final
decision,
to choose the man to lead the mission.
He chooses Nahum Lev,
The deputy chief of the Sayeret Matkal.
>> Nahum Lev, his deputy.
One of the most brave [music] and
legendary figures and different figures
in the history of Sayeret Matkal to lead
the operation.
>> [music]
>> Having read all the available
intelligence,
Lev declares
that Abu Jihad
is a dead man walking.
>> He said, "You know, I read the file on
Abu Jihad. I knew how many Jews, how
many brother Israelis he killed.
I knew that his hands
are covered with Jewish blood.
He deserved to die."
>> Lev's task is to be the first man into
the villa and to locate Abu Jihad.
>> [music]
>> Lev and his men now embark on the
1,500-mi journey to Tunisian [music]
waters.
The quarter-century chase for Abu Jihad
is almost over.
>> [music]
>> At a military base [music] south of Tel
Aviv,
a specially adapted passenger jet takes
off bound [music] for Tunisia.
>> He's ready to see
>> used a electronic warfare aircraft, a
converted Boeing.
>> [music]
>> Barak will command the operation from
the plane, which has been turned [music]
into a flying control center.
A few hours later,
>> [music]
>> the plane reaches Tunisian airspace.
Barak now orders the Mossad team to the
beach.
>> The Mossad was waiting with the rented
cars by [music] the shore, waiting for
the Sayeret Matkal people to come
ashore.
>> With the Mossad agents in place,
the order is given for the Sayeret
Matkal to land.
>> They are taken ashore by members of
Flotilla [music] 13,
Israel's Navy Seals.
>> To minimize sound,
commandos row the last few hundred
meters to shore.
>> The Israelis landed in the dead of
night.
They were picked up by the Mossad
people.
Nobody was there when it came to
Tunisian security.
>> Immediately, the commandos change into
their tourist disguises. [music]
>> They're all changing very quickly. They
change their clothes to civilian
clothes. Some of them are dressed as
women.
The whole group, uh, Mossad, Flotilla
[music] 13, and Sayeret Matkal are
waiting at the beach for the final
go-ahead.
>> [music]
>> As they wait for a green light,
the commandos learn from Barak
that there's a problem.
Israeli intelligence have intercepted a
phone call to Abu Jihad.
>> Someone from the PLO headquarters called
Abu Jihad and said that they were warned
by apparently a European intelligence
service that the Israelis are thinking
of killing a PLO senior figure.
>> Barak's fear is that if Abu Jihad
suspects he might be the senior figure
being targeted,
he may flee Tunis immediately.
>> The Israelis were quite afraid that he's
going to take this threat seriously.
>> [music]
>> Barak demands a report from the Mossad
team watching the villa. Is Abu Jihad at
home or has he fled Tunis?
The agents report
that his Mercedes [music] has been seen
arriving at the villa, but they cannot
confirm that Abu Jihad was in the car.
>> They saw people going out of Abu Jihad's
house and getting [music] into the
house, but they didn't see the face.
>> While Barak waits [music] to find out
where Abu Jihad is, he orders the Mossad
agents at the beach to take the Sayaret
[music] Matkal to their position near
the villa.
>> Quite rapidly, they launched the force
the Sayaret Matkal force [music] from
the beach to Abu Jihad's house.
>> At about 1:00 in the morning, [music]
the three vehicles that contained the
Israeli commandos went into this
neighborhood called Sidi Bou Said.
One vehicle containing eight Israeli
commandos [music] actually went to the
front of the house.
>> But Barak still [music] cannot order the
commandos to launch their assault.
>> Even after forces left the beach and
went on to the house, we still did not
have the right assurance to go in.
>> [music]
>> They were waiting there for the final
approval of the commanders of the
operation that Abu Jihad is indeed at
home.
>> These are the actual words from secret
radio communications between the units
as they wait for the order to proceed.
>> Bogan, Bogan,
this is
Abu Jihad.
I want to tell you it is possible that
there are some people who are not
sleeping in the office.
Okay, Richard. I understand.
>> They use code names and speak in English
instead of Hebrew in case anyone is
listening.
>> Israeli commandos were sitting with
their Uzi submachine guns and pistols
between their legs just waiting for the
signal to proceed.
>> [music]
>> Without absolute certainty that the
target is at home, Barak cannot give the
order to strike.
>> They assured the Minister of Defense
that they will know for sure that Abu
Jihad is in the house before launching
the assault.
>> It is now that Barak shows the Sayeret
Matkal's real quality.
He has a backup plan.
>> Israel is famous for being adjustable.
We change views, we change our behavior,
we change actions according to time and
persons involved. That's a lit unit.
>> A few days previously,
Barak had ordered an operation in the
Palestinian territories.
>> They raid a house in Gaza and arrest a
distant relative of Abu Jihad,
a lawyer.
>> Now in a secret underground basement in
Tel Aviv, a call is made to Abu Jihad's
villa using a specially diverted line.
>> Something that [music] would look like a
phone call from Italy
to Abu Jihad's office in his home.
>> Making the call is an Israeli agent who
pretends to be a Palestinian informing
Abu Jihad of his relative's arrest.
[music]
>> It was shouting and cursing. Abu Jihad,
Abu Jihad, you must help.
They have arrested Abu Rahma again.
These sons of [__] Zionists, they
have arrested Abu Rahma and they are
torturing him.
>> They may hear the voice on the other end
of the line.
>> The speaker says, "Who is there? [music]
Please calm down. We'll make sure
everything is okay. We'll help Abu
Rahma. Don't don't worry."
>> The agent has to keep the person on the
phone talking.
Listening in are three Arabic experts
who have been trained to recognize Abu
Jihad's voice.
>> Each one [music] of them had to raise
his right arm when he's 100% confident
that this is Abu Jihad speaking from the
other side of the line.
>> As the three soldiers listen to the
voice,
first one,
and then another,
raise [music] their right hands into the
air.
>> [music]
>> Finally, the third hand is raised.
>> It was approved and confirmed and
corroborated
that Abu Jihad
is in the house.
>> Finally,
Barak can give the order to strike.
>> Go down. Go down.
This is Richard.
You can leave the station.
Do it fast.
I say it again. Do it fast.
>> Lev, the commander of the operation, and
another commando [music] dressed as a
woman, begin the final approach to the
villa.
Disguised as a romantic couple, they
walk through the [music] busy streets.
>> Hidden in plain sight, nobody would
think twice looking at these guys. Their
task, to approach the villa undetected
and take out the guard on the gate.
>> So, they were a pair walking in the
street carrying a chocolate box.
>> But, the innocuous looking chocolate box
Lev carries actually conceals a gun.
>> They had a weapon hidden under a box of
chocolates.
It's not going to be in a holster and it
won't be slung around the neck.
>> Lev and his partner now approach the
entrance to the villa where the guard is
sat in Abu Jihad's [music] black
Mercedes.
>> They got close to the driver of Abu
Jihad that was still sitting in the car.
>> The woman distracts [music] the guard by
asking for directions.
>> They pulled out the map and they wanted
to ask him some sort of tourist request.
>> As the guard looks over the map,
Lev acts.
Now, the other commandos make their
move.
>> The eight commandos swiftly assaulted
the house.
>> They went to the backyard and came to
the door.
It made some noise
and Abu Jihad heard it in the upper
floor.
>> [music]
[bell]
>> Lev and his accomplice concentrate on
the stairs that will lead to Abu Jihad.
The other team go to take out the
remaining bodyguards.
With the bodyguards dealt with,
Lev and his partner close in on the main
target.
>> One of the assassins of Sayeret Matkal
was going up the stairs. A young officer
of Sayeret Matkal who was chose by Nahum
Lev to be the first one to come in.
>> The commando hears someone at the top of
the stairs.
Is it Abu Jihad
or an innocent member of his family?
The commando knows that he will have to
identify the target in an instant.
The commando reacts instinctively.
>> And then other people from the unit came
and shot Abu Jihad as well.
>> 70 bullets hit Abu Jihad and his right
hand which had held the pistol [music]
was nearly severed.
>> But as they are firing, Abu Jihad's wife
suddenly appears.
>> She screamed, "Hallas! Hallas! Stop it!
Stop it! Don't you see that he's already
dead?"
>> But even with everyone's nerves on edge,
discipline holds.
>> Even when the unexpected
happened, the wife did not get hurt.
We will avoid shooting
even on the expense [music] of getting
hurt.
>> Instead,
>> [music]
>> live orders had to face the wall.
And with Abu Jihad confirmed dead,
the commandos depart.
>> Once it was finished,
they rushed into the cars, back to the
beach, back to the boats, and
>> [music]
>> The entire operation has been
accomplished in a matter of minutes.
>> At dawn, [music] when the Tunisian
investigators and a PLO team went out to
see what happened, all they found were
the three [music] rented vehicles and
footprints on the sand.
>> As the commandos [music]
journey back to Israel,
they know that even by their own high
standards, Operation Show of Force
is an outstanding achievement.
>> Abu Jihad, who as far as the Israelis
were [music] concerned, was the main
planner of the Intifada they were out to
stop,
was dead.
>> But the mission
hadn't been quite flawless.
Despite all the intelligence gathered,
[music] there was something they had
missed.
At the time of the raid, Abu Jihad's
gardener was [music] sleeping in the
basement of the villa.
This innocent man had been killed
alongside Abu Jihad's bodyguards.
Soon news of the operation reaches
Israel.
>> When the uh, troops were on their way
home, it was already published that
someone [music] killed Abu Jihad in his
house.
>> Israel has never formally admitted
to killing
>> [music]
>> Abu Jihad, but there's there was never
really any doubt about it.
But there is a strange twist [music] to
this tale.
The news of Abu Jihad's death does not
have the effect Rabin had hoped for.
It's all very well being clever at
killing Palestinian [music] leaders, but
the PLO didn't disappear.
And the Intifada didn't stop.
In fact, the violence gets worse.
News of Abu Jihad's death triggers the
bloodiest day of protests since the
Intifada began.
And in a bizarre development, the
Israelis learn that despite his claims,
Abu Jihad had never had anything to do
with the Intifada.
>> In fact, he was lying.
He didn't know that the Intifada is
going to break out, he or the PLO. And
they sort of jumped on the wagon after
it started, claimed responsibility for
something that they had no involvement
whatsoever.
>> And the reaction of Israelis wasn't what
Rabin had expected, either.
There was quite a lot of comment in
Israel that, well, this [music] was
brilliantly executed mission by our
boys. At the end of the day, did it make
much difference in the big picture? Not
really.
But one difference it did make
>> [music]
>> was to the career of the man in charge
of the operation,
Ehud Barak.
>> It's hard to [music] overstate what a
legendary career he's had.
>> In the years after the Tunisian mission,
Barak was made chief of the general
staff.
And in 1999,
the Israeli people showed their
admiration for the Sayeret [music]
Matkal
when they elected this former leader of
the unit to become Israeli [music] prime
minister.
The Israeli public though it doesn't
know much about precisely what Sayeret
Matkal has done. Well, the Israeli
public knows [music] that it's a
trustworthy group of men who get things
done.
>> [music]
[music]